<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A defence of the Kings authority and supremacy in the church &amp; church-discipline and that he is supream head and governour over all persons, in all causes ecclesiastical : against these disciplinarians, the Pope and his clergy, the bishops and episcoparians, the Scottish and English Presbyterians, with the independents ... / by Theophilus Brabourne.</title>
            <author>Brabourne, Theophilus, b. 1590.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 62 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A29084</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B4091</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R25285</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08837061</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08837061</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41939</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A29084)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41939)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1277:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A defence of the Kings authority and supremacy in the church &amp; church-discipline and that he is supream head and governour over all persons, in all causes ecclesiastical : against these disciplinarians, the Pope and his clergy, the bishops and episcoparians, the Scottish and English Presbyterians, with the independents ... / by Theophilus Brabourne.</title>
                  <author>Brabourne, Theophilus, b. 1590.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The second edition, much enlarged.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>22, 3 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author, and are to be sold by William Nowell,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Royal supremacy (Church of England)</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:41939:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A DEFENCE OF THE Kings Authority AND SUPREMACY, In the Church &amp; Church-Diſcipline. And that He is Supream Head and Governour, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all perſons, in all Cauſes Eccleſiaſtical. Againſt theſe Diſciplinarians, the Pope, and his Clergy, the Biſhops and Epiſcoparians, the Scottiſh and Engliſh PRESBYTERIANS, with the INDEPENDENTS. Who have for a long time, uſurped the power of Kings, and authority of Magiſtrates, contrary to the will of GOD, and the Honour of KINGS. The ſecond Edition much enlarged. By <hi>THEOPHIL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S BRABO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RNE.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <hi>Give unto Caeſar, the things that are Caeſars.</hi>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for the Author, and are to be ſold by <hi>William Nowell,</hi> Book-ſeller in <hi>Norwich,</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41939:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41939:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A DEFENCE Of The <hi>KINGS S<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>PREMACIE</hi> In the Church and Church-diſcipline: Againſt theſe <hi>Diſciplinarians, the Pope, Engliſh Biſhops, Scottiſh and Engliſh Presbyterians, and Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents: who have for a long time, uſurped the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the King and his Magiſtrates.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>MY enſuing Diſcourſe ſhall be, to maintain the <hi>Kings Supremacy,</hi> in cauſes Eccleſiaſtical, and the authority of all Magiſtrates under him: and to confute the authority of <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and other Miniſters in Church-matters.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe I will not diſpute on Generals, I will by and by come to a particular, namely to the cenſure and puniſhment of <hi>Excommunication,</hi> the which is all the <hi>authority</hi> that Biſhops and Miniſters do <hi>claim:</hi> and I ſhall try whether it belongs to the office of our Chriſtian Magiſtrates, or to the Biſhop and his Chancellour, or to the Miniſter and his Lay-Elders. Now if it can be made appear, as I believe it will, that the cenſure of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication belongs to the Magiſtrate and not to the Biſhop, then Biſhops have loſt all their authority, even the richeſt flower in their Garland,</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:41939:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>By the way note, that as the inferiour Miniſters rule with their Lay-Elders, ſo doth the Biſhop with his Chancellour, who is no Miniſter, but a Lay man: and thus you ſee, that all Diſciplinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans have their Lay-Elders.</p>
            <p>Now my endeavour ſhall be to give unto <hi>Caeſar</hi> our King, the things that are <hi>Caeſars:</hi> and to his ſubordinate Magiſtrates, the things that are theirs: and to give unto Biſhops and Miniſters, the things that belong to them; as to be <hi>Preachers,</hi> not <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> like Magiſtrates I have 2 or 3 things more to premiſe before I come to my task.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Near twenty years agone, I took the Nationall <hi>Oath</hi> and <hi>Covenant,</hi> to be true and faithfull to the King and his Poſterity; the which I have been ever ſince, ſo far as in my power was, ſorrowing to ſee ſo many illegall and treacherous practiſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond my power to amend. I then alſo did <hi>ſwear,</hi> to do my <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour</hi> for the <hi>extirpation</hi> of <hi>Prelacy,</hi> that is, of <hi>Archbiſhops, Biſhops,</hi> and <hi>Chancellors,</hi> &amp;c. In purſuance whereof I writ this little Treatiſe: holding my ſelf bound in conſcience to keep my Oath.</p>
            <p>But it will be ſaid, the Parliament when they required this Oath was then illegall, the King being abſent.</p>
            <p>I anſwer. Hence it follows, that my Oath was illegall, and binds not in the Common Law; but yet it binds in point of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity:</hi> For an Oath taken by <hi>force</hi> and <hi>feare,</hi> binds, as in the caſe of the Oath taken to the King of <hi>Babel,</hi> Ezek. 17.12, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And an Oath taken by <hi>fraud</hi> binds, as in the caſe of the <hi>Gibeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nites:</hi> and no man on earth can abſolve from ſuch an Oath, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 9.3, 4.18, 19. with 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.1, 2.6. wherefore I dare not be a perjured perſon. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> ſaid, <hi>Becauſe of Oaths, the Land mourns,</hi> Jer. 23.10. God plagued the Iſraelites in <hi>Davids</hi> time, for the perjury of <hi>Saul</hi> before him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 21.1, &amp;c. We have ſins enough in this Land to anſwer to God for: and ſhall we add wilfull perjury to them, to provoke the Lord to wrath? God forbid. Now I humbly beſeech our honourable <hi>Parliament,</hi> to order things ſo, as thoſe who have taken this Oath, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be recall'd, may not be enforced by Law, to be forſworn by any of their endeavours to eſtabliſh or countenance our new Biſhops.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:41939:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="2">2. Many ſay, as King <hi>James</hi> did: no <hi>Biſhop,</hi> no <hi>King;</hi> but King <hi>James</hi> was no Prophet, he ſpake as he thought and deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: But had he lived to our dayes, and ſeen what we have ſeen, he might have changed his proverb. If I may be ſo bold to ſpeak my ſenſe, it had been good for King <hi>Charles,</hi> his Son, if he had caſt off Biſhops twenty years before his death: For, as I ſuppoſe, they were one great cauſe of his untimely end.</p>
            <p>For he had armed his Biſhops with too much of his Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; the which ſome of them abuſed to <hi>pride,</hi> calling them <hi>Jack Gentlemen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moſt of them abuſing his authority, for the uſhering in of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh <hi>Ceremonies,</hi> ſpending their <hi>zeale,</hi> to maintain trifles, not beſeeming learned and grave Doctors: as an ayeriall Croſs, and white Surplice, an Hood and Tippet, whereby they became <hi>ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diculous</hi> to the people:</p>
            <p>And then they abuſed his authority, to cruelty and <hi>perſecution</hi> for thoſe trifles: How many hundreds of painfull and godly Miniſters, of a good life and converſation, did they ſilence for non-obſervance of theſe, and unmercifully deprived them of their livings and livelihood, ſo as they were enforced to live up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Almes.</hi> So great was their <hi>perſecution</hi> in thoſe dayes, as they drove many hundreds of the Kings <hi>Subjects</hi> out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to plant themſelves in a <hi>Wilderneſs:</hi> And how great was their tyranny in the High <hi>Commiſsion</hi> Court at <hi>London,</hi> and their <hi>Chancellours</hi> Courts in the Country, perſons of years know too well: and all this for trifles, whereby they became <hi>odious</hi> to the people then, and to thoſe that ſate at the beginning of this long <hi>Parliament</hi> after, who rooted them quite up: For theſe were eye-witneſſes, and ſenſible of the pride, ambition, and cruell perſecutions of the Biſhops, whereof many in our dayes being but young men, are totally ignorant, and therefore think to ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther grapes of theſe thorns, and Figs of theſe thiſtles: But a wolf will be a wolf ſtill, though you crop his eares, and cut his tayle, the ſame is true of a Fox.</p>
            <p>Now in proceſs of time, when unhappily the King and Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment fell at odds, many thouſands of the people took in with the Parliament, ſome help them with money, others with their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and ſwords: but would not take in with the King, for feare
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41939:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> of <hi>Popery,</hi> and for feare they ſhould be ſtill under the tyranny of cruell <hi>Biſhops;</hi> the which to conſcientious men, was more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable than monethly <hi>Taxes,</hi> or illegall <hi>Monopolies</hi> of old. Thus the King loſt the hearts of his Subjects, becauſe they ſaw themſelves in a <hi>deſperate</hi> caſe: For it was grown into a proverb, no Biſhop, no King.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Many who have read my former book of this ſubject, ſay, that I am an <hi>Eraſtine,</hi> but they are ſuch as know not the opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Eraſtus.</hi> I have ſeen his book, which was anciently a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute between reverend <hi>Beza</hi> and him, about Excommunication. Now <hi>Eraſtus</hi> held it to be no Ordinance of Chriſt, but a figment of mans brain: but I differ from him, and hold it to be an Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance of Chriſt, I onely endeavour to ſet the ſaddle on the right horſe, ſaying, It is the office of the Magiſtrate, not of the Biſhop or Miniſter.</p>
            <p>Theſe things premiſed, now I come to my taske, and ſhall handle by ſundry queſtions and anſwers thereunto drawing nea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer and nearer unto it by little and little, untill I come to the main. The conſideration whereof, may prove uſeful to the <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Parliament:</hi> For deſire them I do, to be cautious of putting their own ſword into the hands of the <hi>Clergy,</hi> leſt they turn the point of it againſt Magiſtrates: Have not the Scots excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated their King? and may not our Biſhops (if true to their principles) do the ſame to any Member in Parliament, or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate in the Kingdome? Yea, to the King himſelfe: as I ſhall prove before I have done, and ſo I come to the queſtions.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Queſt. <hi>Who are the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I anſw.</hi> Not the <hi>Clergy</hi> onely, but the <hi>Laiety</hi> &amp; <hi>Clergy</hi> both, not excluding, but including the Magiſtrate: For the Magiſtrate is not onely a member of the Common-wealth, but alſo a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Church: He is an <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> perſon as well as the Miniſter: for he is <hi>of</hi> and <hi>belonging</hi> to the Church as well as the Miniſter: and ſo much is ſignified by the word <hi>Eccleſiaſticall:</hi> Wherefore you may not object againſt the Magiſtrate, ſaying, he may not meddle with Excommunication, becauſe he is a Lay-man: For we muſt know, that the Magiſtrate is an Eccleſiaſtical perſon as well as the Miniſter.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, the Miniſter is a <hi>Spirituall</hi> man, ſo is not
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41939:4" rendition="simple:additions"/> the Magiſtrate. I anſw. He is a <hi>ſpirituall</hi> man that minds ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things, and leads a <hi>ſpiritual life, Rom.</hi> 8.1, 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.6. Now God be praiſed for it, we have many Magiſtrates, who are ſpiritual men, and lead a ſpiritual life; and many thouſands of common people, who are ſo too: but Biſhops, and Clergymen, and the Pope, will be the ſpiritual men, and Magiſtrates and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers muſt be the <hi>carnal</hi> men.</p>
            <p>Whereas I ſaid even now, the <hi>Laiety</hi> and Clergy: I ſhall be quarrelled with by the Clergy, for giving the <hi>priority</hi> to the Laiety, and not to the Clergy, as hath been the cuſtome for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred years. Now I grant, that it hath been the cuſtome ever ſince there was a <hi>Pope,</hi> and ever ſince the Pope exalted himſelf above all that is called God; that is, above the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.4. and ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. And this Popiſh cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, would Biſhops and Clergy-men uphold ſtill: But are not the <hi>King,</hi> Parliament, and Magiſtrates Lay perſons, as they call them? and are not theſe above the Clergy? If theſe then be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Biſhops and Clergy-men, theſe muſt have the priority; as well as ſuperiority: and therefore I ſaid, the <hi>Laiety</hi> and Clergy: to ſay otherwiſe is Popiſh, and tending to a denyall of the Kings <hi>ſupremacy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 2. <hi>How are the members of the Church to be qualified?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſw. Not ſpeaking of the <hi>inviſible,</hi> but of the viſible Church on earth, theſe muſt have faith and repentance, or at leaſt a <hi>profesſion</hi> of theſe: now that this latter makes a member of the Church, I thus prove it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Baptiſme is the <hi>door</hi> into the Church, and ſuch as were bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized were <hi>entred</hi> into the Church, and admitted as <hi>members</hi> of the Church: Now <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, baptized a great multitude, as <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and all <hi>Judea,</hi> and all the Country about <hi>Jordan,</hi> upon <hi>confeſsion</hi> of their ſins, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.5, 6. Now <hi>John</hi> could not know any more of theſe, then their verball profeſſion, and yet he admitted them into the Church by baptiſme. 2. The 3000. converted and baptized by <hi>Peter,</hi> and ſo admitted into the Church, he could know no more of them then their <hi>externall</hi> profeſſion, by <hi>ſubmiſsion</hi> to his baptiſme, and by ſaying <hi>men and brethren what ſhall we do?</hi> which were but words. True, the Text ſaith, <hi>they were pricked in heart,</hi> Acts 2.37. But how could
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41939:5" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> know this; ſave by their words; and ſubmiſſion to his bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme? both which were externall: The Text ſaith, <hi>verſ.</hi> 45. <hi>they ſold their poſſeſsions to give to the poor,</hi> yet <hi>Ananias</hi> was a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.1, &amp;c. See 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.19. &amp; <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.20. Further, the people of <hi>Laodicea</hi> were a Church, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.14. yet many of them had but externall profeſſion. <hi>Simon</hi> the Sorcerer was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, and ſo made a member of the Church, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.13. and <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> was a member of Chriſts family and Church.</p>
            <p>By the way note, that there is a <hi>ſuperſtitious niceneſs</hi> in ſome, who will not admit one a member of their Church, without a moneths tryall, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but this is after the doctrine and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of <hi>men, Col.</hi> 2.22, 23. not after the practice of <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt.</p>
            <p>To return: If a Magiſtrate hath but an outward profeſſion, he is a member of the Church, and an Eccleſiaſticall perſon, as well as a Miniſter: Let none therefore ſay, he is a Lay-man, and therefore he may not meddle with Excommunication, as a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter may.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 3. <hi>Is a Magiſtrate an Elder and Ruler of the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſw. He is not onely an Elder and Ruler of the Common-wealth, but alſo of the <hi>Church:</hi> this later I thus prove.</p>
            <p>Theſe called the Elders and Rulers of the people of this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, <hi>Numb.</hi> 11.16, 24. were Rulers of the <hi>Church</hi> alſo; For <hi>Moſes</hi> commanded <hi>Aaron</hi> the chief Prieſt, to offer Incenſe, which was a Church-matter, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.46. King <hi>Hezekiah</hi> did the like, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.2. King <hi>David</hi> did ſo too, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.7. And alſo King <hi>Joſiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.4. and 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35 15.1, 2, 3, &amp;c. <hi>Things written afore-time, were written for our learning,</hi> Rom. 15.4. Hence it follows,</p>
            <p n="1">1. If therefore a Magiſtrate be a <hi>Ruler</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> why may not he puniſh the ſcandalous ſinner in the <hi>Church?</hi> and that with any puniſhment ſutable to the offence? be it by their puniſhment of Excommunication, or any other puniſhment: it is in vain for him to command, if he may not puniſh.</p>
            <p n="2">2 If a Lay-Elder, be he the Biſhops Chancellor, or the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters Elders, may puniſh with Excommunication; why may not the Magiſtrate do ſo too? though you call him a Lay-man.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, the Lay-Elder doth it not alone, but with the Miniſter.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:41939:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> If he doth it with another, yet he doth it, though not alone. The chief Prieſts and Elders together, put Chriſt to death: Yet we may ſay, and ſpeak truly, the Elders put Chriſt to death.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 4. <hi>Do you make two Churches in one Common wealth, the one of the Magiſtrates, the other of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſw. Yea: for they hold the Congregation and Aſſembly of the Miniſter and people, in the <hi>Pariſh-houſe,</hi> to be one Church: and I ſhall prove, that there is another Church, as in the <hi>Senate-houſe,</hi> or common <hi>Hall,</hi> where the Magiſtrate and people, are congregated and aſſembled for matters of Juſtice.</p>
            <p>For the word <hi>Eccleſia,</hi> tranſlated a Church, ſignifyeth a Congregation, or an Aſſembly of people, <hi>Acts</hi> 7.38. <hi>Acts</hi> 19.32, 39, 41. Now the Magiſtrate and people in the Senat-houſe, are a Congregation and an Aſſembly of people: and therefore they are a Church, and all of them are <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> perſons, of and belonging to this Church.</p>
            <p>As the Magiſtrate and people are a Church, ſo they are a Church of Chriſt; for they are all Chriſtians, profeſſing Chriſt, and faith in Chriſt, and they are alſo a Church of <hi>God:</hi> for their authority is of, and from God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. and they aſſemble in their <hi>Hall</hi> to ſerve God; The Magiſtrate by ruling for God, and in his place; the people to be ruled by God, and his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Lawes.</p>
            <p>The Magiſtrates <hi>Court</hi> therefore, being a Church of <hi>God,</hi> why ſhould any ſay or think, that it is an unfit <hi>place,</hi> for the cenſure of Excommunication? may it not ſoon be as fit a place, as the Chancellours or Biſhops Conſiſtory?</p>
            <p>Another queſt. of theſe two Churches, which is greater? Papiſts ſay, the Clergy Church, ſo they ſay, Biſhops too; for they ſay, <hi>Church and State:</hi> but we ought to give priority and ſuperiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the State, and ſay, <hi>State and Church:</hi> For <hi>Moſes</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Aaron,</hi> and ſo did Kings the Prieſts: to ſpeak otherwiſe, gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving priority to the Church, is popiſh, and tending to a denyall of the Kings ſupremacy.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 5. <hi>Being the Magiſtrate is no Divine, how can he know who is fit or not fit to be excommunicated?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:41939:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>I anſw. How can two or three Lay-Elders, know who is fit, and who not, being they are no Divines? And how can the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Chancellour know, who is fit, and not fit? for he is no Divine.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As for <hi>ſcandalous</hi> ſins, as adultery, drunkenneſs, ſwearing, and ſuch like, being all matters of <hi>Fact,</hi> the Magiſtrate knows them, as well as the Biſhop or Miniſter, for the Magiſtrate doth daily puniſh theſe ſins in his Court.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>fundamentall</hi> doctrines, being none are ſuch, but onely ſuch as are <hi>clearly</hi> laid down in Scripture: and being they are daily preached on by our Miniſters, the Magiſtrate is not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of theſe: Or if he be, God hath ordained the help of the Miniſter, by way of counſel and advice: but ſtill ſo, as the power and authority as Judge to paſſe cenſure, is ſtill in the Magiſtrate, as you may read, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17.8, 9, 10, 11.</p>
            <p>As for points <hi>diſputable,</hi> not cleerly revealed in Scripture, I hold, that no man is to be excommunicated for theſe; for if he be, the innocent may be puniſhed, as ſoon as the wicked. And therefore the Magiſtrate needs not meddle with ſuch points, but onely with ſins clearly revealed to be ſins, as <hi>inceſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and by like reaſon, ſwearing, drunkenneſſe, and the like.</p>
            <p>Whereas I ſaid, the Magiſtrate may take the advice of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, &amp;c. I mean his advice in a fundamentall doctrine, which is very <hi>cleerly</hi> a ſin in Scripture; for elſe he may give wicked ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice: But as for a doubtfull and diſputable controverſie, wherein Scripture is alledged on both ſides, it is not ſafe for the Magiſtrate to condemn either ſide upon advice of the Miniſter: for a <hi>Church</hi> may erre, a <hi>Councell</hi> may erre, and 10. or 12. <hi>Miniſters</hi> may erre too. Suppoſe therefore a point comes before the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, which <hi>commonly</hi> is holden to be an error or <hi>hereſie,</hi> where will the Magiſtrate finde among the <hi>Clergy</hi> competent and fit Judges to determine it? for the Clergy hold the common opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion: Now if the Magiſtrate call in to his help and advice ten or 12. of the Clergy, will they not all adviſe for their own opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? and then they will be incompetent and partiall Judges: Do you think, they will juſtifie the accuſed party, and condemn themſelves? I dare ſay it, that all the Biſhops in <hi>England,</hi> will
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:41939:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> condemn this book if not before they ſee it: But the Law per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits no man to be a judge or a witneſs in his own cauſe: when the <hi>Clergy</hi> gives judgement, of a cauſe commonly holden by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and themſelves, to be an errour or hereſie, they are like the High <hi>Court</hi> of <hi>Justice,</hi> all or the major part came thither with a reſolution, to make an end of the <hi>KING</hi> before they roſe.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 6. <hi>Is the King next under Chriſt, ſupreme head of the Church?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> This queſtion is out of queſtion with me: but being I hear of ſome Miniſters beyond Sea offended at this <hi>Title,</hi> and have read of ſome in <hi>England</hi> of like opinion, I ſhall here prove the point: and firſt by the Laws of our Kingdome, and then by the Scripture.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Laws of our Kingdome, do give unto our <hi>King</hi> this juſt and Royall title, to be <hi>ſupreme Head</hi> under Chriſt, over all perſons, and in <hi>all</hi> cauſes <hi>Eccleſiaſticall</hi> or ſpirituall: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the King is ſupreme haad of the Church, and therefore all good Subjects muſt acknowledge him ſo to be, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I have before proved, out of the Scriptures, that King <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zekiah, David,</hi> and <hi>Joſiah,</hi> were Rulers and Governours over the Church, and in <hi>Church</hi>-matters, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 31.2. &amp; 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.7. &amp; 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.1, &amp;c. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.15. &amp; 2 <hi>King.</hi> 23.4. Now thoſe godly Kings were <hi>ſupreme</hi> in authority, for there was none above or before them. It was propheſied of, that in time of the Goſpel, <hi>Kings</hi> ſhould be our nurſing <hi>Fathers,</hi> Iſa. 49.22, 23. Now in our dayes, though we have many Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of high authority, yet none of them can or will challenge the ſupremacy, but the King onely.</p>
            <p n="3">3. See a pregnant Text for it, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. <hi>Submit your ſelves,</hi> &amp;c. unto the <hi>King,</hi> as unto the <hi>ſupreme.</hi> So ſupremacy is the Kings juſt Title. Now being it is ſo, why do Biſhops ſay and write <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State?</hi> as if the Church and Biſhops were above the King: where is then the Kings ſupremacy?</p>
            <p>Queſt. 7. <hi>Doth the puniſhment of Excommunication belong to the office of a Biſhop and his Chancellour: or to the Miniſter and his Lay-Elders?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer negatively: This office belongs not to any <hi>Lay-El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:41939:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> who is not a Magiſtrate of the Common-wealth: nor to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Chancellour,</hi> who is a Lay-man, and no Magiſtrate: the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, I expect to ſee Biſhops or Miniſters to prove if they can. And I anſwer, concerning Biſhops or Miniſters alone, without their Elders or Aſſiſtants; and I deny alſo, that this office doth belong to a Biſhop or a Miniſter: The contrary lyes upon both of them, to prove if they can. In the mean time I thus prove a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Excommunication is a <hi>puniſhment,</hi> ſo confeſſed by all men, and ſo called in Scripture, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. and a puniſhment is a <hi>revenge,</hi> or taking <hi>vengeance</hi> on them that do evill, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. Now Biſhops and Miniſters may not puniſh, and revenge: For this belongs to the Magiſtrate, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. not to a Biſhop or Miniſter.</p>
            <p>St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, a <hi>Biſhop</hi> muſt be no <hi>ſtriker,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.3. Now I know not why a Biſhop may not as well ſtrike with his <hi>hand</hi> or <hi>fiſt,</hi> as puniſh, and take vengeance on any man by Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Their diſtinction of corporall and <hi>ſpirituall</hi> puniſhment will not help them, as you ſhall ſee in the next queſt.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The office of the Magiſtrate is, to <hi>ſummon</hi> into his <hi>Court,</hi> theſe ſcandalous ſinners, the adulterer, ſwearer, drunkard, and the like, and in his Court to <hi>examine</hi> them, and to examine <hi>witneſſes</hi> againſt them, and then if guilty, to judge and <hi>cenſure</hi> them to puniſhment, all theſe are acts of Magiſtraticall autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and we daily ſee Magiſtrates exerciſing this authority. Now for Biſhops to uſe theſe ſeverall acts in their Conſiſtorie, it is an <hi>uſurpation</hi> of the Magiſtrates office and authority: and therefore this authority belongs not to a Biſhop or a Miniſter, nor to the Pope: and without theſe precedent acts of authority, there can be no Excommunication.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath forbidden the Pope, the Biſhop of a Dioceſs, and the Miniſter of a Pariſh, to exerciſe <hi>Lordly</hi> authority in the Church: for he ſaid, <hi>The Lords of the Gentiles exerciſe dominion, and they that are great, exerciſe authority: But it ſhall not be ſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you,</hi> Mat. 20.25. Chriſt forbad his Apoſtles to Lord it; and St. <hi>Peter</hi> to like purpoſe ſaid, That Miniſters muſt not be ſo much <hi>as,</hi> or <hi>like</hi> unto <hi>Lords,</hi> over <hi>Gods heritage,</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. Now for a Biſhop to puniſh with the <hi>Rod</hi> of Excommunication,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:41939:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> it is a Lordly authority, for puniſhment is Lordly: and for a Biſhop in his Conſiſtory, to examine one, and witneſſes againſt him, and then to judge and condemn him to puniſhment, this is Lordly authority: wherefore the cenſure of Excommunication belongs not to a Biſhop.</p>
            <p>I ſhall proſecute this point further, by ſundry <hi>abſurdities</hi> which depend upon it, as</p>
            <p n="1">1. If Excommunication be proper to a Biſhop, or a Miniſter, why doth the Biſhops Chancellour meddle in it? for he is a Lay-man: and why do the Miniſters Elders meddle in it? for theſe are Lay-men.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If the Biſhop will puniſh <hi>ſome ſins</hi> by Excommunication, as <hi>Adultery,</hi> then he muſt puniſh <hi>all ſins</hi> with Excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for if he doth not, he is <hi>partiall</hi> and <hi>unjuſt.</hi> The Biſhop hath but one <hi>ſalve</hi> for every ſore, but one <hi>laſt</hi> for every foot, which is Excommunication for greater and leſſer ſins: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he muſt inflict this one puniſhment upon every ſinner: and then he muſt excommunicate every thief, every traytor, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very murtherer before they are hanged: and there are a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of treſpaſſes by the Common Law, the which are ſins alſo: Now all theſe the Biſhop muſt ſummon into his Conſiſtory, for to undergo his ſpirituall puniſhment.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Magiſtrate puniſheth in his <hi>Court,</hi> the adulterer, drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kard, ſwearer, &amp;c. Now the Biſhop and his Chancellour, may not puniſh theſe in his <hi>Conſiſtory</hi> again with Excommunication; for if they do, they commit <hi>injuſtice:</hi> For after the Magiſtrate hath inflicted a full puniſhment, then for a Biſhop to bring the matter about again for another puniſhment: this is to puniſh twice for one fault, a double puniſhment for a ſingle ſin: It is a torment intollerable, and apt to make men run mad, to be trounced from the Magiſtrates Court, unto the Biſhops Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for one crime, to be twice examined in ſeverall Courts, to have witneſſes twice brought againſt them, to be twice cenſured and condemned, and to ſuffer two ſorts of puniſhments, and all for one fault, which hath been ſufficiently puniſht before by the Magiſtrate: this is intollerable.</p>
            <p>To avoid this miſchief, either let the Magiſtrate do all acts of authority and juſtice, without the Biſhop: or let the Biſhop
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:41939:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> and his Chancellor, do all acts of authority and juſtice, in things Civill and Eccleſiaſticall, without the Magiſtrate; For to have two ſuch Magiſtrates, a corporall, and a ſpirituall, or a Civill, and an Eccleſiaſticall, is as if we had two Suns in the Firmament, or two Kings in <hi>England,</hi> the Pope was the author of it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If Excommunication be exerciſed by a Biſhop, then he makes himſelf an <hi>Antichrist,</hi> or <hi>Pope:</hi> For in his Conſiſtory, he ſits as a Judge over a Magiſtrate if he be ſcandalous, examines him, and witneſſes againſt him, cenſures and condemns him: Now the <hi>marke</hi> of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> is to <hi>exalt himſelfe above all that is called God,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.4. And the Magiſtrate is called <hi>God, Pſal.</hi> 82.6. If therefore a Biſhop doth paſſe ſentence upon a Magiſtrate, he makes himſelf Antichriſt.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 8. <hi>Is excommunication a ſpirituall puniſhment belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Biſhops?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I take this to be a popiſh device, and invented by the <hi>Pope:</hi> For when he <hi>encroached</hi> upon the authority of <hi>Kings,</hi> that he might with the more colour obtain leave from them, to <hi>reigne</hi> over the ſouls of the people, leaving the bodies and fleſhly car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kaſſes for Kings to Reign over, then he ſtifled them with this Doſe; that Excommunication is no corporall but a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, and ſutable to his <hi>ſpirituall</hi> Clergy: and this hath been the doſe and plea of our Biſhops ever ſince.</p>
            <p>But why the Clergy ſhould engroſs this <hi>ſpirituality</hi> as proper to them, I ſee no reaſon: For a Magiſtrate is an Eccleſiaſticall perſon, and a <hi>ſpirituall</hi> man, as well as a Biſhop: for he is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual man that worſhips God in ſpirit and truth: and who minds ſpiritual things, and live after the guidance and motions of the ſpirit, <hi>John</hi> 4.23. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.1, 5. <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.6. Now we have as many Magiſtrates, ſuch ſpirituall men as Biſhops: and therefore Magiſtrates are as fit to exerciſe the ſpirituall diſcipline of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication as a Biſhop: this I thus prove.</p>
            <p n="1">1. If a Biſhops Chancelleour who is a Lay-man, or the Lay-Elders of Miniſters, may meddle in ſpirituall Excommunication, then a Magiſtrate may do ſo too, though you call him a Lay-man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>Excommunication,</hi> if it be a ſpirituall puniſhment, yet it is in the <hi>power</hi> of the Magiſtrate, it is cleer, <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.3, 7, 8.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:41939:8" rendition="simple:additions"/> where the <hi>Princes</hi> and Elders, did by a Proclamation, threaten the people with <hi>Excommunication,</hi> or ſeparation from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, if they came not to take the <hi>Covenant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. King <hi>Solomon</hi> put off <hi>Abiathar</hi> the Prieſt, from his ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all office of Prieſthood: which degradation was a <hi>ſpirituall</hi> pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.27. as his office was a ſpirituall bleſſing.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If <hi>Excommunication</hi> be a <hi>ſpirituall</hi> puniſhment, yet it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not to a Biſhop, becauſe it is a <hi>Lordly</hi> power, forbidden by Chriſt to Miniſters, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.25. &amp; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3.</p>
            <p n="5">5. If a Biſhop uſeth this ſpiritual puniſhment of <hi>Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> he makes himſelf an <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and a <hi>Pope;</hi> as I lately proved.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 9. <hi>Can you prove, that the cenſure and puniſhment of Excommunication belongs to the Magiſtrate?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer yes: But firſt give me leave to ſhew what, and how the Magiſtrate is to act in this his office: when he hath ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned into his Court the Adulterer, Swearer, Drunkard, &amp;c. and hath examined him, and witneſſes againſt him, and hath convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted him as guilty of puniſhment, then he is to paſſe ſentence on him publiquely in Court, to ſuffer ſuch puniſhment as is ſutable to his ſinne: and if the Magiſtrate judgeth Excommunication to be more ſutable then any other puniſhment, then he is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce the ſentence thereof upon the offender: And this done, then he is to ſend his command to the Biſhop or Miniſter of the pariſh to deny him the Sacrament. I doubt not, but the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate may command the Biſhop or Miniſter: For <hi>Moſes</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded <hi>Aaron, Hezekiah</hi> and <hi>Joſiah</hi> commanded the Prieſts and Levites; and ſo I come to prove the point.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The cenſure and puniſhment of <hi>Excommunication</hi> muſt either belong to the Biſhop or Miniſter, or to the Magiſtrate: But it belongs not to the Biſhop or Miniſter, as I have abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly proved before. Therefore it belongs to the Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The <hi>Princes</hi> and Elders in <hi>Ezra's</hi> time, commanded the people to come to <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to take the <hi>Covenant,</hi> and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thoſe that refuſed, with <hi>excommunication</hi> or <hi>ſeparation</hi> from the Congregation or Church, <hi>Ezra</hi> 10.3.7, 8. whereby you ſee that <hi>excommunication</hi> was in the power of the Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p n="3">3. King <hi>Solomon</hi> degraded <hi>Abiather</hi> the Prieſt from his ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:41939:9"/> office, which was a ſpirituall puniſhment, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.27. Now if Kings and Magiſtrates will imitate <hi>Solomon,</hi> then they muſt excommunicate ſcandalous perſons: <hi>Solomon</hi> put off the Prieſt from medling in holy things, ſo ſhould Magiſtrates cut off ſcandalous ſinners from the communion of Saints at the Lords Table, and from medling with theſe holy things.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If the Magiſtrate may command ſpirituall duties, then he may inflict ſpirituall puniſhment for neglect of them, as in <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication:</hi> He that may command a duty, hath power to puniſh the neglect of it, or elſe he hath no power to command: to command without a coercive power to compell, is but an i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage or ſcare-crow: But the Magiſtrate may command ſpiritual duties, 1 <hi>Chron.</hi> 16.7. &amp; 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.15. &amp; 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 29.1, 4, 5. &amp; 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.4. And therefore the Magiſtrate may inflict the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall puniſhment of <hi>Excommunication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Excommunication</hi> is a puniſhment, and ſo called by all men, and ſo it is called in Scripture, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. and a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is a <hi>revenge.</hi> Now to puniſh and revenge is proper to the Magiſtrate, for he is the Miniſter of God, to puniſh and to take <hi>vengeance on him that doth evill,</hi> Rom. 13.4. Wherefore the cenſure of Excom. upon the ſcandalous ſinner, belongs to the office of the Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The ſeverall acts of authority uſed in Excom. belongs to Magiſtraticall power, as to ſummon into Court, and to examine witneſſes againſt one, and to examine the perſon complained on: And without theſe precedent acts, there can be no Excom. Now to whom belongeth theſe acts, to him belongeth the cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of Excom. that is, to the Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p>By theſe particulars it appears, that by the Word of God, the Biſhop in his Conſiſtory doth <hi>uſurp</hi> the Magiſtrates office.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 10. <hi>Do Biſhops deveſt the King of his ſupremacy?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer yes: and thus I prove it.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is clear by the Word of God, as hath been proved, that Biſhops do <hi>uſurp</hi> the Magiſtrates authority and office: Now he that uſurps the Magiſtrates authority, he uſurps the Kings au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, for the Magiſtrates authority is the Kings: and he that uſurps the Kings authority in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall, he denies and deveſts the King of his ſupremacy in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall:
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:41939:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> For if you deny him authority, you deveſt him of, and deny his ſuperiority and ſupremacy in authority. If a Maſter gives his ſervant five pounds, to diſpoſe of by his order, and the ſervant be robbed of it by the way, not onely the ſervant is robbed, but his Maſter alſo: and then his money being loſt, he can exerciſe neither authority nor ſuperiority over it: So it is, if a Biſhop takes from the Magiſtrate the Kings authority, with it he takes the Kings ſuperiority and ſupremacy in Eccleſiaſticals.</p>
            <p>But Biſhops will ſay, they had the Kings <hi>Commiſſion</hi> for it: and the King <hi>gave</hi> them this authority. But ſay I, <hi>Chriſt</hi> forbad them to <hi>take</hi> it, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.25. and 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3.</p>
            <p>Secondly, they ſay the King gave it them; and ſo doth a true man give his purſe to a Thief, but it is out of <hi>fear:</hi> So theſe Kings afore-time, gave their authority to Biſhops, but they got this gift by <hi>fraud:</hi> For the Pope perſwaded Kings, that the <hi>Key</hi> of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline and Juriſdiction was a <hi>Legacy</hi> left by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> firſt to Saint <hi>Peter,</hi> and ſo to his ſucceſſors, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.19. which is falſe, and more then can be proved. Beſides, <hi>Chriſt</hi> forbad the Pope and Biſhops to exerciſe Lordly authority, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.25. &amp; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. Now as the Pope, ſo did thoſe Biſhops falſly plead that Legacy, and ſo got it by fraud and ſubtlety: wherefore as I conceive, the gift of thoſe Kings, and their Commiſſions was a <hi>nullity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Cromwell</hi> of late, got off the Kings head by <hi>force:</hi> and thus Biſhops got away thoſe Kings regall authority in the Church by fraud and ſubtilty: Would it not grieve a man to ſee his friend cheated of his money at Dice? And how can it but be grievous to a loyall Subject, to ſee his Kings juſt and Royall prerogative, wreſted out of his hands by the wit of Biſhops?</p>
            <p>In King <hi>Henrie</hi> the 8. the Biſhops of <hi>England</hi> took an Oath to the <hi>Pope;</hi> whereupon the Lord <hi>Cromwell</hi> then informed the King of it, ſaying, that he was but half King, and his ſubjects but half-ſubjects to him: As I conceive, that the King was King but over the bodies, and Biſhops were Kings over the ſouls of the people: ſo they fell into a <hi>premunire,</hi> which coſt them 100000. pounds. The Biſhops in thoſe dayes could not by flattery and ſubtlety perſwade the King and his Council, that St. <hi>Peters</hi> keyes did hang on the Popes girdle, or on the girdle of <hi>Engliſh Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops:</hi> he would not be ſo cheated of his ſupremacy, for they got it by fraud.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:41939:10"/>
            <p n="2">2. The Pope holds his office <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> ſo did thoſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and ſo do our Biſhops: for all theſe plead for <hi>Peters</hi> keys, and ſuch like Scriptures: Now though our Biſhops take a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the King, and ſay he is ſupreme, yet they hold a higher <hi>commiſsion,</hi> namely from God and Chriſt, and the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures: How then can the King be <hi>ſupreme</hi> in cauſes Eccleſiaſtical? for Biſhops have a commiſſion higher then the commiſſion which they have from the King: And how can he be next under Chriſt, when the Biſhops have gotten the <hi>higher</hi> Commiſſion? The King may be ſupreme over the State, but Biſhops are next to Chriſt, and ſupreme over the Church, and in cauſes Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall; for they ſay, they have an immediate commiſſion from Chriſt: If ſo, their commiſſion from the King muſt be an inferi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our commiſſion.</p>
            <p n="3">3. If a <hi>Biſhop</hi> hath this Lordly authority to Excommunicate, then if he makes <hi>conſcience</hi> of his office, he muſt do <hi>juſtice</hi> to and upon all men, rich and poor, noble and ignoble, even to the K. as well as to the peſant: God is no reſpecter of perſons, a Biſhop muſt not be partiall. Now if a King be ſubject to a Biſhops Court, and the Biſhops there ſits as <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Judge</hi> over him, where is the Kings <hi>ſupremacy</hi> in <hi>Eccleſiaſticals?</hi> Notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Biſhops conſciences and doing of juſtice, I know they dare not ſummon the King into their Conſiſtory: Yet I know, and they know too, that by their <hi>principles,</hi> and the power of <hi>Peters</hi> keyes, which hang at their girdle as they make the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, they are bound to make no ſcruple of any man, noble or ignoble.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Diſcipline is odious to <hi>Epiſcoparians,</hi> for excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municating their King: but in my opinion, the <hi>Scots</hi> are the more honeſt men, for they act according to their principles: but Biſhops halt of one leg, and are blind of one eye, when they look upon a King; and yet the <hi>Scots</hi> and our Biſhops do fetch their authority both from the ſame Scriptures. If therefore they may excommunicate the King by their <hi>principles,</hi> where is the Kings ſupremacy?</p>
            <p n="4">4. There is a <hi>ſecret</hi> deſigne of <hi>Biſhops</hi> for <hi>ſupremacy,</hi> for they write and ſay <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State:</hi> Now though common people regard not which end goes forward, yet <hi>Biſhops</hi> do: for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:41939:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> they do not onely write ſo, and ſpeak ſo, but will have others to ſpeak ſo too: my ſelf being with a <hi>Biſhop</hi> long ſince, I ſaid <hi>State</hi> and <hi>Church:</hi> but the <hi>Biſhop</hi> corrected me, ſaying, you muſt ſay, <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> So <hi>Biſhops</hi> will have priority and ſuperiority over the State: and if ſo, then they aym at the Kings ſupremacy, for he is a Stateſ-man, and the chief of the State, there can be no ſupremacy, where there is not priority &amp; ſuperiority. How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the <hi>Biſhops</hi> do act openly for the Kings ſupremacy, yet <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derhand,</hi> they aime at the old Popiſh ſupremacy: why elſe do they keep on foot, that popiſh language of Church and State?</p>
            <p>The <hi>Biſhops</hi> alſo uſe to name the <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Laiety,</hi> giving the priority and ſuperiority to the <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Biſhops:</hi> but where then is the Kings priority, ſuperiority, and ſupremacy? Alſo they uſe to ſay, <hi>Lords ſpirituall</hi> and <hi>Lords temporall.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 11. <hi>Are Miniſters capable of a Biſhopricke, or the office of a Biſhop?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer negatively, and my reaſons are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As is before proved, <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath forbidden Miniſters to uſe Lordly authority in the Church, <hi>Mat.</hi> 20.25. &amp; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.3. and therefore Miniſters are not capable of a Biſhoprick.</p>
            <p n="2">2. If a Miniſter takes upon him the office of a Biſhop, he makes himſelf a <hi>Pope</hi> or an <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> who <hi>exalts himſelf above all that is called God,</hi> 2 Theſ. 2.4. Who is the Magiſtrate, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. For in his Conſiſtory, he ſits as Judge over both Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate and people.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The office of a Biſhop by ruling, is contrary to the office of a preaching Miniſter, as I thus prove.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſent his Apoſtles to <hi>preach,</hi> Mat. 20.1, 2, 7. but not to <hi>rule.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> charged <hi>Timothie</hi> not to rule, but to <hi>preach,</hi> and <hi>be inſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon,</hi> 2 Tim. 4.2. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Woe unto me, if I preach not the Goſpel,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.16. And Miniſters had their <hi>Ordination,</hi> not to rule, but to preach.</p>
            <p>But Lordly Biſhops are no Preachers: no ſooner Biſhops, but their heads are ſo full of Proclamations with ruling, as they lay aſide preaching. Queen <hi>Eliz.</hi> when ſhe went to make a Biſhop ſaid, <hi>I am now going to ſtop a Preachers mouth.</hi> I can ſpeak my knowledge of them for ſixty years, that they preach not above once a yeare, ſometimes twice, ſometimes not once. Biſhops
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:41939:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> have ever been Miniſters, but never Preachers: they have been the <hi>Drink</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive, the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> in Gods Vineyard, &amp; thoſe that have <hi>hidden</hi> their <hi>Talent</hi> in the earth, or in a dark <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>; did not ſuch Biſhops well deſerve 2000. or 3000. pounds a year? ſurely the State in thoſe times, knew not what to do with their money. As for thoſe that ſate at the beginning of the long parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, though I cannot call them legall, the King being abſent, yet I look upon them, as an <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of the wiſe men of our Kingdome: and thoſe judged it good for the Church to root our Biſhops, Archbiſhops, Deans, Chancellours, &amp;c. and theſe wiſe men were eye-witneſſes and ear-witneſſes, and had too long an experience of Biſhops miſcarriages, the which our young dayes cannot afford us.</p>
            <p>They ſaw with their eyes, how the <hi>heart</hi> of Religion was in a Conſumption; and how Religion was like a garden over grown with the nettle and weeds of humane inventions, and Biſhops, or rather the Popes inventions, untill Ceremony had well nigh eat up ſubſtance: all was for an outward form and faſhion, as to bow towards the Eaſt, and then to turn Weſt: To go up to the high Altar, and then come down again to the Deske, to be clad in white, and in the Pulpit to be clad in black, as if God were pleaſed with ſuch toyes: but I ſhall tell you of many more of theſe Ceremonies before I have done. One thing more I believe provoked theſe wiſe men, which was the Biſhops cruell <hi>perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> ſilencing and depriving of livelihood, very many godly and painfull Miniſters, men of a blameleſs life and converſation, and all for non obſervance of popiſh Ceremonies: and another thing was, that they drove hence many of the Kings Subjects, to plant in <hi>New-England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Queſt. 12. <hi>Are Biſhops allied, or a kin to the Pope, or are they Popiſh?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have often ſaid, that Biſhops Ceremonies are Popiſh, and now I ſhall prove it, by ſhewing their affinity to the Pope.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> is a Clergy-man, a Biſhop, and a Lord-Biſhop, and ſo were our Engliſh Biſhops.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Pope hath theſe many <hi>Orders</hi> of Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Deans, Commiſſaries, Chancellors, Arch-deacons, Prebends, and the reſt of them: ſo have our Biſhops, as like to the Pope as may be.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:41939:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="3">3. The Pope reigns over many Nations: and our Biſhops, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hundreds of Towns and Pariſhes; and the Arch-biſhop, by reaſon of a larger circuit, is yet nearer the Pope.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The Pope challengeth the <hi>Lordly</hi> power of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and ſo do our Biſhops.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Pope <hi>exalts himſelf above all that is called God,</hi> that is, the Magiſtrate: and ſo did our Biſhops in their Conſiſtory.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Pope is a Miniſter, but no preacher: ſo were our Biſhops, Non-preachers: As ſoon might you draw a Bear to the ſtake, as a Biſhop into a pulpit: and if at once in a year, then they came trapped with their popiſh veſtments. Biſhops had high Altars in their Chappels, and wax Candles thereon unlighted, a fit Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleme of a Biſhop without light in a pulpit: They would be theſe <hi>Angels, Rev.</hi> 1.20. but they were not the <hi>Angels of light:</hi> for they gave no more light than their wax candles, unleſſe on Chriſtmas day in the forenoon.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Pope was a cruell perſecuter of godly proteſtants: ſo were theſe Biſhops of many godly painfull Miniſters, men of an honeſt life and converſation, theſe they ſilenced from preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: (The dog in the manger would eat no hay, nor ſuffer the horſe to eate) and they unmercifully deprived them of their Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vings and livelihood, ſo as the Miniſter, his wife and children were enforced to live upon <hi>Almeſ-deeds.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="8">8. Biſhop <hi>Wren,</hi> whilſt Biſhop in <hi>Norwich,</hi> forbad the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters in his Dioceſs, to make any prayer in the pulpit, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an exhortation to prayer, according to the 55. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non: as pray we for the King, or let us pray for the ſick, &amp;c. but the Miniſter was not ſuffered to put up one petition to God, for the <hi>King,</hi> or for the <hi>ſicke.</hi> If this be according to the 55 Canon, then all the Biſhops were of this mind. Alſo papiſts do ſing their <hi>Maſs:</hi> ſo in our Cathedral Churches, Biſhops do ſing, cant, and chant their <hi>Service.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">9. The Pope was horribly <hi>ſuperſtitious,</hi> ſo were theſe Biſhops: for both of them had their Croſs in baptiſm, the Surplice, hood and tippet, Copes, high Altars, Waxe Candles, Rails before the high Altar, bowings towards the high Altar, Saints dayes, ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up at the Creed, with others like. Biſhops ſaid, theſe Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies were <hi>innocent</hi> and <hi>decent</hi> things: but they have been <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:41939:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> with <hi>ſuperſtition,</hi> as I read in their <hi>Canons:</hi> and are things defiled now innocent? and are popiſh ceremonies decent things in a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Church?</p>
            <p>Thus it appears that the Pope and thoſe Biſhops were much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, and neerly allyed, and that I have done them no wrong, by ſaying they were popiſh: For I read not in <hi>Scripture,</hi> of <hi>Arch-Biſhops, Lord-Biſhops, Deans, Chancellours,</hi> &amp;c. nor of a Croſſe in the ayre on an Infants fore head, nor of Surplices, Hood, and Tippet, nor Copes, Wax-candles, Rails, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Theſe never were plants of Gods ſetting, but of the Popes: I cannot therefore bow to this <hi>golden Image</hi> which the Pope hath ſet up.</p>
            <p>The Popiſh <hi>Maſs</hi> doth crawl full of theſe Ceremonies, and ſo doth our Biſhops <hi>Divine Service</hi> in Cathedrall Churches, the which is one cauſe, why many people do ſo loath the Service-book: for where the Service-book comes in, there comes in theſe <hi>Romiſh ceremonies:</hi> and we have a <hi>ſuperſtitious Clergy,</hi> as ready and nimble to bid them welcome as may be.</p>
            <p>Theſe Biſhops therefore, being ſo like the Pope in cruel <hi>perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution</hi> of godly Miniſters, in <hi>ſuperſtitious ceremonies,</hi> and in <hi>ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Orders</hi> of Archbiſhops, Deans and Chancellours, &amp;c. and being ſuch <hi>loyterers</hi> in Gods Vineyard, and <hi>hiding</hi> their talent of light in a cloſe Lanthorn; thoſe at the beginning of the long Parl. did us a good office to remove them quite: and I wiſh the King had been in preſence, to have confirmed it, and annexed their Lands to the Crown Lands, where they would have done good: but now they do none, but to maintain a Colledg of lazy perſons; but that which hindred our happineſs, was an over high carriage then with the King, for which we have ever ſince ſmart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed full ſore.</p>
            <p>Queſt. 13. <hi>Is there no meanes to pacifie and allay the animoſity between Biſhops and Epiſcoparians, Independents, and the Scottiſh Diſciplinarians, that ſo we may have peace in the Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſw. Yes, there is one means, and but one that I know of; which is, that the King would take his own ſword into his own hands, and manage in by his Magiſtrates, who are capable of it, as I have abundantly proved, and diſcharge <hi>Biſhops, Preſbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Independents,</hi> and <hi>Scottiſh, Diſciplinarians</hi> of their Lordly power. This Kingly ſword is the <hi>bone</hi> of contention among them
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:41939:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> all, untill it be removed. I never look to ſee peace in the church: but if once removed, I hope to ſee theſe perſons, for highly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting, feed and play together like Lambs, and love like Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A word or two of falſe Tranſlations.</head>
               <p>I Do find, by reading of learned <hi>Expoſitors</hi> on the <hi>Bible,</hi> that many words and Texts concerning the bleſſed Trinity, are falſely tranſlated: I hold it my duty, no longer to conceal it, but to make it known, that it may come to the knowledge of the King and Parl. who I hope will take it into conſideration, and in due time ſee that it be amended: And for a taſte, I will give you ſome of the Texts, and ſhall be ready to ſhew many more.</p>
               <p n="1">1. See <hi>Eccl.</hi> 12.1. Remember thy <hi>Creators:</hi> ſo it is plurally in the Hebr. Text, as if there were more then one Creator of the World: And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>God created all things by Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Epheſ. 3.9. But it is falſely tranſlated <hi>Creator</hi> ſingularly, as if there were but one.</p>
               <p n="2">2. See <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149.2. <hi>Let Iſrael rejoyce in his makers:</hi> ſo it is plurally in the Hebr. Text, as if there were two or three makers of the world: And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>God made the world by his ſonne, Heb.</hi> 1.1, 2. But it is falſly tranſlated <hi>Maker,</hi> or <hi>Him</hi> that made; as if there were but one.</p>
               <p n="3">3. See <hi>Gen</hi> 1.2. <hi>The ſpirit of the Gods moved on the waters:</hi> ſo it is plurally in the Hebrew; as if there were two or 3 Gods: But it is falſly tranſlated <hi>God</hi> ſingularly, as if there were but one God.</p>
               <p n="4">4. See <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.12. <hi>And ye were without Gods in the world:</hi> ſo it is in the Greek Text plurally, as if there were more then one God in the Trinity: But it is falſly tranſlated <hi>God</hi> ſingularly, as if there were but one God in the Trinity.</p>
               <p n="5">5. See <hi>Gen.</hi> 20.13. <hi>When the Gods, they cauſed me to wander:</hi> ſo it is in the Heb. Text plurally, both noun and verb are plural, as if there were two or three Gods in the Trinity. <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3.22. <hi>The man is become like one of us.</hi> but it is falſly tranſlated ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, both in the noun and verb, as <hi>God cauſed</hi> me: as if there were but one God in the Trinity.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:41939:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p n="6">6. See <hi>Gen.</hi> 35.7. <hi>The Gods, they appeared unto him.</hi> So it is plurally in the Hebr. Text, both the noun and verb are plurall: as if there were two or three Gods, as God the Father, God the Son, and God the holy Ghoſt: But it is falſly tranſlated, both in in the noun and verb ſingularly, as <hi>God appeared:</hi> as if there were but one God in the Trinity.</p>
               <p>The Church ſaith, there is but one God: Now Tranſlators, unfaithfully to maintain the Doctrine of the Church, tranſlate falſly, to draw <hi>Scripture</hi> to the Church: but like honeſt men, they ſhould tranſlate word for word, number for number, to draw the <hi>Church</hi> to the Scriptures.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41939:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Poſtſcript, further proving, that Biſhops uſurp the Kings Authority, and devest him of his Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy.</head>
            <p>THe King is the <hi>Fountain</hi> of all Authority and Juriſdiction: and whoſoever exerciſes Juriſdiction in this Kingdome, wtthout authority from the King, they uſurp the Kings authority, and make voyd his ſupremacy; and this Biſhops do: For</p>
            <p n="1">1. There are two eſſentiall parts of a Biſhops office as they hold, <hi>Ordination</hi> and <hi>Juriſdiction.</hi> Now they lay as much claim to the power of <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> as to <hi>Ordination,</hi> and receive them both from the ſame hand and Donor: As the one therefore is from God, not from the King, ſo is the other, even both from one and the ſame Donor, but neither of them from the King. 2. a Biſhop is created, by his <hi>Metropolitan</hi> and other Biſhops, who by <hi>Impoſition</hi> of their hands, do confer upon him as from God, the office of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction as they ſay, now this Office is not derived from the King, nor can be: for the King doth not <hi>lay hands</hi> on the Biſhop created. 3. Biſhops claim their authority and juriſdiction in the Church, from <hi>Peters</hi> Keys <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.19. but not from the King, for <hi>Peters</hi> Keys were not delivered to <hi>Kings</hi> or lay perſons, but to the <hi>Clergy.</hi> 4. All this Biſhops confeſt in their writings, concerning this ſimilitude, the patron gives the Benefice or Living to the Incumbent, but the Biſhop gives him his orders; ſo the King gives the Biſhoprick to the Biſhop, that is his large maintenance of 2 or 3000. a yeare, but God gives him his Office, and makes him a Biſhop: ſo then a Biſhop doth derive his Office of juriſdiction from the King. 5. Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in diſputation ſay their Office is <hi>Ius Divinum:</hi> ſo then they own not the Kings Authority in Eccleſiaſticals: for this is <hi>Ius Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the premiſes it is cleare, 1. That Biſhops have and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe as high Authority in the <hi>Church,</hi> os the King hath in the <hi>Common Wealth:</hi> how then can the King be ſolely next <hi>under Chriſt?</hi> yea, the Biſhops have the ſole authority in the Church, but the King
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41939:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> hath none at all: where is then the Kings authority, ſuperiority, and ſupremacy in Eccleſiaſticals? the Biſhops have all authority from God, in themſelves: they derive none from the King: wherefore they <hi>own not</hi> the Kings authority, ſoveraignty, ſuperiority, nor ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy: no more then Papiſts do.</p>
            <p>True it is, that Biſhops <hi>pray</hi> for the King as ſupreme, and uſe their authority in his <hi>name:</hi> but for all this, as you have ſeen they do not <hi>own</hi> his authority, but deny it: they do but diſſemble: for when they ſpeak really and cordially, they reject his authority: but when they intend to flatter, then in words, they <hi>pray</hi> for the King as ſupreme, Thoſe <hi>Exorciſts,</hi> Act 19.13. did name over thoſe that had evil ſpirits, the name of the Lord Jeſus: but had no au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſo to do, and their end was evil: ſo Biſhops, uſe the name of the King and his authority: but have no authority from the King ſo to do as you have ſeen proved: wherefore they uſurp his authority: and their end therefore cannot be good.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Two or three things added to my poſtſcript, further proving that Biſhops were Popiſh.</head>
               <p>SInce my former writings, a booke came to my hands, intituled, <hi>Reaſons for the neceſſity of a reformation in Diſcipline &amp;c.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I note beſides others, 2 things: and I ſhall add a third.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That Biſhops have foiſted into the Book of Common Prayer many <hi>Apochriphal</hi> Scriptures, which by the Law ought to be read in Churches: and which worſe is, they have rejected 100 Chapters of the ſacred <hi>Canonical</hi> Scriptures, and placed 100. Chapters in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of them, of Apochryphal Scriptures: <hi>Oh abhominable fact!</hi> do they deſerve the name of proteſtant Biſhops, who <hi>Pope-like,</hi> make Apochrypha Scriptures, of equal authority with the Holy word of God? was it not high time for the long <hi>Parliament</hi> to root them out?</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the <hi>Letany</hi> of old, there was this Proteſtant prayer <hi>from the Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Rome, and all his deteſtable enormities, Good Lord deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver us,</hi> but in our books of Service, afterwards printed, this prayer was rejected by Biſhops, and not one word of it, were not thoſe Biſhops think you, greater friends to <hi>Papiſts</hi> than to <hi>Proteſtants?</hi> for they would not ſuffer us to pray againſt Popery.</p>
               <p n="3">3. About 50 years agone, Biſhops perſecuted many godly and
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41939:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> painfull Miniſters for the <hi>Croſs</hi> and <hi>Surpliſſe,</hi> but within about 20. year after, what a troop of popiſh ceremonies more did they peſter our Church withall? then they brought in 1. <hi>High Altars</hi> 2. The <hi>ſecond ſervice</hi> at the high Altar. 3. <hi>Bowings</hi> and cringing towards the Eaſt and the high Altar. 4, <hi>Waxe Candles</hi> on the high Altar in Biſhops Chappels. 5. <hi>Railes</hi> before the high Altar. 6. the Sacrament was denyed to thoſe that refuſed to come up to the high Altar for it: I cannot re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member all their trinkets 100. <hi>Apochriphal</hi> Chapters inſtead of 100 Canonical Chapters. 8. No <hi>prayers</hi> to be made for the <hi>King</hi> in pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit. 9. That the <hi>prayer</hi> in the Letany, againſt <hi>popery,</hi> muſt no more be uſed. All theſe have ſprung up long ſince my time: and had not the long Parliament prevented it, by rooting out Biſhops, we may feare that by this time or not long hence, <hi>England</hi> would have been another <hi>Rome.</hi> Judge I pray by theſe particulars, whether that was true or not, which I wrote at the beginning of this Book ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, not only Biſhops tyranny, but alſo the <hi>feare</hi> of <hi>popery,</hi> cauſed thouſands of the people to deſert the King, at the beginning of the unhappy warr. Thoſe that had eyes in their heads might eaſily ſee what a crew of Popiſh Biſhops we had: for my part I never look to ſee them better, unleſs for a moneth or two or ſo long as our <hi>Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious King</hi> live: who I beleeve will <hi>awe</hi> them for his time: but what ſhall become of us afterward?</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
